Guide to the Newman Smyth Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Newman Smyth papers
1874-1924
1908-1924
MS 623
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, diaries, sermons, and other papers of Newman Smyth, theologian, author, and pastor. The papers relate largely to Smyth's interest in and work on behalf of Protestant unity; there is little material for the period prior to his retirement from the ministry in 1908. Important correspondents include bishops and officials in the Anglican and Protestant Episcopal churches, other churchmen and theologians, and laymen interested in his work, most notable George Wharton Pepper and George Zabriskie.
Smyth, Newman, 1843-1925
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Winifred Smyth, 1939.
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks are available on microfilm (100 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM126.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings, Diaries, and Statements. III. Special Files. IV. Scrapbooks.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Phillips Newman Smyth was born on June 25, 1843 in Brunswick, Maine. He was the son of William Smyth, professor of mathematics at Bowdoin College, and Harriet Porter Coffin Smyth. He had five brothers and sisters, among them a brother who became professor of Church History at Andover Seminary.
Smyth received his education at Phillips Academy in Andover, Mass.; Bowdoin College (1863); and Andover Theological Seminary (1867). Between his years of college and seminary he served first as an assistant librarian and professor of Mathematics at the United States Naval Academy, and then as a second lieutenant of the 16th Maine Volunteers in the Union Army. He fought during the last year of the Civil War and was present at Lee's surrender.
Smyth was ordained in 1863 and a year later he went to Germany, where he was exposed to and influenced by modern biblical criticism. On his return to the United States he served as pastor to three churches: The First Congregational Church of Bangor, Maine (1870-1875); the First Presbyterian Church of Quincy, Illinois (1875-1882); and the First Church of Christ of New Haven, Conn. (1882-1908). While in New Haven he was made a fellow at Yale University.
In 1871, Smyth married Anna Marston Ayer. They had four children: Mary Winslow (b. 1873), Nathan Ayer (b.1876), Winifred (b. 1881), and Ethel (b. 1885). Smyth wrote approximately twenty books on theology, religion and science, and church unity during his life time. His early works employed biblical criticism against the prevailing "New England Theology", and it was his views, particularly those on "second probation", that caused great controversy over his appointment to the Abbot Chair of Christian Theology at Andover Theological Seminary.
In 1908 Smyth retired from the New Haven church and became pastor emeritus. He then devoted most of his energy attempting to discover a basis for Protestant unity. His principal activities centered around three proposals aimed at unification. The first, the Lenox Proposal, was a plan for a limited union of certain functions of the Protestant Episcopal and the Congregational Churches. The second was an appeal for practical unity and joint ordination of chaplains during World War I. The third involved a plan for a special Episcopalian ordination that would be acceptable to the Congregational Church. Though each of these proposals eventually met defeat Smyth was a strong proponant of unification until his death on January 6, 1925.
Though Newman Smyth was an active and productive theologian during the first two-thirds of his life, the largest part of the Newman Smyth Papers relate to his activities after his retirement from the ministry in 1908. With the exception of four folders of correspondence pertaining to Smyth's call to the First Church of Christ in New Haven and a controversial and abortive appointment to the faculty of Andover Theological Seminary, both occuring in 1881-1882, almost all of the correspondence in this collection centers around the topic of church unity. Likewise, with the exception of his photo-diary of a trip to the Orient, Egypt, and Palestine in 1901 and his sermons from the 1870s through 1880s, the majority of Smyth's diaries and writings relate to Church unification.
Series III, "Special Files," contains the minutes, reports and resolutions of the organizations in which Smyth participated or was interested in, as well as newspaper and magazine clippings and pamphlets commenting on people, organizations and the events in the unification movement.
As a result of his interest in pan-protestantism, Smyth corresponded with many of the leading churchmen of his time, particularly with members of the Anglican and Protestant Episcopal Churches. He corresponded with over a third of the Bishops of the Episcopal Church. In addition, Smyth corresponded with two laymen, George Wharton Pepper (later U.S. Senator from Penn.) and George Zabriskie, as well as a number of theologians and leaders of other denominations. This correspondence contains personal and official statements on many subjects including the nature of communion, ordination, and church organization. The correspondence, writings, and other material assembled in these Papers provide a view of the variety of inter and intra-denominational views on these subjects in the first quarter of the century.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, diaries, sermons, and other papers of Newman Smyth, theologian, author, and pastor. The papers relate largely to Smyth's interest in and work on behalf of Protestant unity; there is little material for the period prior to his retirement from the ministry in 1908. Important correspondents include bishops and officials in the Anglican and Protestant Episcopal churches, other churchmen and theologians, and laymen interested in his work, most notable George Wharton Pepper and George Zabriskie.
Religion; Theology; Asia; Middle East; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Abbott, Lyman, 1835-1922; Anderson, Charles Palmerston, 1863-1930; Brewster, Chauncey B. (Chauncey Bunce), 1848-1941; Bridgeman, Howard Allen, 1860-; Davidson, Randall Thomas, 1848-1930; Gore, Charles, bp. of Oxford, 1853-1932; Hall, Francis J. (Francis Joseph), 1857-1932; Morehouse, Frederic Cook, 1868-1932; Pepper, George Wharton, 1867-1961; Smyth, Newman, 1843-1925; Zabriskie, George Albert, 1868-1927; Episcopal Church
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1881-1882, 1908-1924; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into two sections: "General Correspondence" and a brief section of "Correspondence of Others." Both sections are arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter or under the name of the person or organization to whom the letter was addressed.
  The number in the parentheses indicates the number of items in the folder
  - General Correspondence
    - A - B, 1908-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A - B (3), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Abbot, Lyman, Burton, The Rt. Rev. Lewis (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ainsley, Peter (15), 1912-1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Association for the Promotion of Christian Unity (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, The Rt. Rev. Charles P., Bishop of Chicago (11), 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anderson, The Rt. Rev. Charles P., Bishop of Chicago (23), 1915-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Andover Theological Seminary and Bowdoin College. Corres. re: Teaching Position. (9), 1881-1882 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      General
      See also: box 2, folder 48
    - Armitage, The Rev. Clyde M., General Committee on Army and Navy Chaplains (3), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Altwater, E. E. (3), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bell, The Rev. George K. E., Resident Chaplain to the Archbishop Canterbury (2), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brent, The Rt. Rev. Charles H., Bishop of Western New York (17), 1918-1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brewster, The Rt. Rev. Chauncey B., Bishop of Connecticut (17), 1908-1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bridgeman, Howard A., Editor-in-Chief, The Congregationalist and (4), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Buckhorn, John Wright, Pacific School of Religion (7), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - C-F (22) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - C - F (7), 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chesire, Rt. Rev. Joseph B. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Courtney, Francis (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dinsmore, Charles A. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Douglas, George William (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Ely, Lord Bishop of (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Colkins, Raymond (4), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Davidson, Randall Thomas, Arch-Bishop of Canterbury (8), 1914-1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Davies, The Rt. Rev. Thomas F., Bishop of Western Mass. (6), 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Davis, Ozoras, President of Chicago Theological Seminary (3), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - First Church of Christ (New Haven.) corres. re: Call to preach in New Haven., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - First Church of Christ (New Haven) letter requesting permission to print a sermon (1), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Frere, The Rev. W. N., The Community of Resurrection (3), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - G - K, 1908-1924 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - G - K (7), 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Greer, The Rt. Rev. David H. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hall, The Rt. Rev. C. A. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hamilton, The Rt. Rev. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hugel, Baron Friedrich von (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gailor, The Rt. Rev. Thomas F., Bishop of Tennessee (4), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Gibson, The Rt. Rev. Robert A., Bishop of Virginia (3), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Gore, The Rt. Rev. Charles, Bishop of Oxford (England) (11), 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Guerry, The Rt. Rev. William A., Bishop of South Carolina (2), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hall, Francis Joseph (9), 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Henson, The Rt. Rev. Herbert Hensley, Bishop of Durham (2), 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - King, Henry C., President of Oberlin College (3), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - L - O, 1908-1924 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Lawrence, The Rt. Rev. William, Bishop of Massachusetts (7), 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Lines, The Rt. Rev. Edwin S., Bishop of New Jersey (11), 1918-1924 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Manning, The Rt. Rev. William T., Bishop of New York (5), 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Morehouse, Fredric Cook, Editor of The Living Churchman (13), 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - National Council of Congregational Churches, corres. with Sanders, Frank K., and Burton, C. E. (3), 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - National War Council of the Y.M.C.A.; corres. with Mott, John R.; Stevenson, J.; Stronger, Paul M.; Barbour, C.H.; and Stocking, J.J. (7), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Nelson, The Rt. Rev. Richard H., Bishop of Albany (5), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - North, Frank Mason, Corres. Secretary, Board of Foreign Missions (5), 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - P - S, 1908-1924 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - P - S (5), 1917-1924 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Roberts, W. H. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Reese, Freerick Focke (Georgia) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Shipler, Guy Emery (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Pepper, George Wharton (11), 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Pepper, George Wharton (12), 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Rhinelander, the Rt. Rev. Philip, Bishop of Pennsylvania (4), 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Sabatier,(?) Paul (2), 1909 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Slattery, the Rt. Rev. Charles Lewis, Bishop Coadjutor of Massachusetts (9), 1917-1924 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Smyth, Egbert C. (brother to N.S.), Andover Theological Seminary (4), 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - T - W, 1908-1924 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Talbot, the Rt. Rev. Ethelbert, Bishop of Bethlehem, Pa. (13), 1915-1920 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Tuttle, the Rt. Rev. Daniel S., Presiding Bishop (12), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Vincent, the Rt. Rev. Boyd, Bishop of Southern Ohio (14), 1917-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Weller, the Rt. Rev. Reginald H., Bishop of Fond Du Lac (21), 1915-1922 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - White, Charles A. (5), 1882 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Williams, the Rt. Rev. Charles David, Bishop of Michigan (3), 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Wilson, the Rt. Rev. St. John Basil Wynne, Bishop of Bath and Wells (2), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - World Conference on Faith and Order, Corres. with the Rt. Rev. Charles P. Anderson, William T. Manning, and Robert H. Gardiner. (5), 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      See also: box 4, folder 7
    - Zabriskie, George (17), 1918-1923 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Fragments (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Unidentified letters (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - The Rt. Rev. Chauncey Brewster to The Rev. Dr. Lynch (3), 1923 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - The Rt. Rev. Edwin Lines to Miss Du Bose, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Edmund T. Shanahan to William E. Hicking, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Walker, Williston; letter to--Washburn (1) (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Walker, Williston; letters written to Walker from The Rev. William Barton, George Wharton Pepper, The Rt. Rev. Philip Rhimelander, Truman Spencer, and George Zabriskie.(5), 1921 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- WRITINGS, DIARIES, AND STATEMENTS, 1876, 1885-1886, 1889, 1901, 1908, 1914-1923; Series II; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series is grouped by type of material as follows:
  Journals
  Sermons
  Speeches and Articles
  Open letters and Signed Statements
  Writings of Others
  - Journals
    - Photo-Journal (handwritten) of Tour of Egypt, Palestine and the Orient, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - I Chronicles 12:32.
      See: box 3, folder 20
  - Sermons
    - Psalm 45:11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Psalm 127:1.
      See: box 3, folder 21
    - Proverbs 13:23.
    - Isaiah 33:24 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Isaiah 64:4 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Matthew 1:17 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Matthew 21:9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Matthew 5:9
    - Matthew 26:8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Matthew 28:16 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Mark 10:32 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Luke 2:1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Luke 15:15 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Luke 16:10 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Luke 19:28 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Luke 22:22 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - John 5:17 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - John 6:19 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - John 11:56 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - John 15;14 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - John 17:16 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - John 21:3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - John 21:17 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - John 19:15.
    - Acts 1:3 (two versions) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Romans 8:3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Romans 16:12 (two versions) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Ephesians 1:10 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Philippians 4 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - II Thessalonians 1:11 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Hebrews 2:14 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Hebrews 12:27 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - I Peter 5:7 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - II Peter 1:13 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - III John 8 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Revelations 22:17 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "The Spirit of Christ," (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Speech concerning religious experience (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Fragments (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Speeches and Articles
    - "Social Problems: Sermons to Workingmen", 1885 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Scientific Patriotism", 1889 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "The Religious Principle in American Politics", 1876 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Social Caesarism", 1886 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "The Spiritual Quality of Evolution", undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Claims of Labor," "Use and Abuse of Capital," "Social Helps."
    - "College Leadership", undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "The Making a City", undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Report given to the General Conference of Congregational Churches, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Untitled speeches on the nature of thinking and on education, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Speech at World Convention on Faith and Order, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Other Bodies and Movements", undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "The Waldensian Church", undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "The Christian Ministry", undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified fragments (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "The Bull Apostolicae Curae and the Validity of Sacrements", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "The Churches of the United States and the War", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "A Call for a Covenant of Church Unity" Untitled speeches, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Suggestions for the Work of the Joint Commission", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "The Order of Topics in Their Relative Values", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Unrealists", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Untitled (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified speeches, articles and misc. statements re: Church Unity, 1896, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified speeches, articles, and misc. statements re: Church Unity, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Misc. notes (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Open Letters and Signed Statements
    - Letters to the editor written and/or signed by Newman Smyth, 1914-1921, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Appeals for support for church unity, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Writings of Others
    - Manuscripts re: Church unity (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - The Rt. Rev. Durlington, address to annual convention, diocese of Harrisburg, Dr. Hall, "The Value and Limits of Federation" (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Manuscipts re: Church unity (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Rev.Dr. Herring, "Congregational Ordination" (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - George Wharton Pepper, on Lenox Proposals Williston Walker, on S. Goulart (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Letters to the editor from The Rt. Rev. Charles H. Brent, The Rt. Rev. Chauncey B. Brewster, The Rt. Rev. William T. Manning, The Rt. Rev. Boyd Vincent (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Clippings and articles re: Church unity, 1918,1914, 1918-1919, 1908, 1914, 1916-1919, 1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 37-39)
    - Pamphlets re: Church unity, 1908, 1915, 1921, 1908, 1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
- SPECIAL FILES, 1908-1924; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  SPECIAL FILES consists of minutes, reports and resolutions relating to church unity followed by newspaper clippings about Newman Smyth.
  - Commission of Nineteen on Polity - Reports (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commission on Comity, Federation and Unity Reports, minutes, proceedings (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - House of Bishops (Protestant Episcopal) Reports, minutes, proceedings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Interchurch Council on Organic Union, and American Council on Organic Union Reports, minutes, proceedings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Joint Commissions on Concordat Reports, minutes, proceedings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lambeth Conference (Anglican) "An Appeal from the Bishops.…to All Christian Peoples," "The Lambeth Conference Appeal. The Response." (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - World Conference on Faith and Order Reports, minutes, proceedings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    General note
    See also: box 2, folder 57
  - Other organizations involved in church unity Reports, minutes, proceedings, etc. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Press clippings about or mentioning Newman Smyth, 1914-1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
- SCRAPBOOKS, 1874-1895; Series IV
  Newspaper clippings of sermons, letters to the editor, book reviews by and about Newman Smyth. Also included are clippings on issues and events in which Smyth was engaged, e.g. Sunday closings, temperance, legal and political reform.
  These scrapbooks have been filmed (HM film 126; MAY 1982). After filming the originals were discarded.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1874-1879 (Reel 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1894-1895 (Reel 1)
    [Transferred from the Divinity Library, July 1978.]